Finding aid for the Smothers Brothers Scripts for The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour PASC.0069
UCLA Library Special Collections
Smothers Brothers Scripts for The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour
1967-1969
UCLA Library Special Collections
Smothers Brothers
Smothers, Dick
Smothers, Tom, 1937-
PASC.0069
16.0 linear feet (16 boxes)
The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour, starring the folk singing, comedy duo Tom and Dick Smothers, premiered on CBS in February 1967. The controversial television variety show featured regulars such as Pat Paulsen, Leigh French, and Bob Einstein and guest performers such as countercultural icons like the Jefferson Airplane and the Doors to established favorites such as Kate Smith and Jimmy Durante. The collection consists of bound volumes of scripts for The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour television show.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Smothers Brothers, 1976.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9929769413606533
Biography/History
The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour, featuring the folk singing, comedy team Tom and Dick Smothers, premiered on CBS in February 1967. The variety show attracted a younger, politically engaged audience. The show's content featured irreverent digs at many dominant institutions such as organized religion and the presidency. It also included sketches celebrating the hippie drug culture and material opposing the war in Vietnam. These elements made The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour one of the most controversial television shows in television history. The Smothers Brothers' oppositional politics led to very public battles over censorship. As CBS attempted to dictate what was appropriate prime time entertainment fare, the Smothers tried to push the boundaries of acceptable speech on the medium. The recurring skirmishes between the brothers and the network culminated on 4 April 1969, one week before the end of the season, when CBS summarily threw the show off the air. Network president Robert D. Wood charged that the Smothers had not submitted a review tape of the upcoming show to the network in a timely manner. The Smothers accused CBS of infringing on their First Amendment rights.
The brothers typically opened the show with a few minutes of stand-up song and banter and the show's final segment usually involved a big production number, often a costumed spoof, featuring dancing, singing and comedy. Guest stars ran the gamut from countercultural icons like the Jefferson Airplane and the Doors to older generation, favorites like Kate Smith and Jimmy Durante. Nelson Riddle and his orchestra supplied musical accompaniment, and the show had its own resident dancers and singers. Regular performers included Tom Smothers, Dick Smothers, Pat Paulsen, Leigh French, Bob Einstein, Mason Williams (1967-1969), Jennifer Warnes (1967-1969), John Hartford (1968-1969), Sally Struthers (1970), Spencer Quinn (1970), Betty Aberlin (1975), Don Novello (1975), Steve Martin (1975,) and Nino Senporty (1975).
The show, appearing at a pivotal moment of social and cultural change in the late 1960s, ended up embodying some of the turmoil and pitched conflict of the era. In the aftermath of the show's cancellation in 1969, the Smothers received a great deal of support in the popular press. Tom Smothers attempted to organize backing for a free speech fight against CBS among Congressional and Federal Communications Commission members in Washington D.C. While they were unsuccessful in forcing CBS to reinstate the show, the Smothers did eventually win a suit against the network for breach of contract. In the years following their banishment from CBS, the Smothers attempted to recreate their variety show on the other two networks. In 1970, they did a summer show on ABC, but were not picked up for the fall season. In 1975 they turned up on NBC with another variety show which disappeared at mid-season. (Historical information from: The Encyclopedia of Television; https://www.museum.tv/eotv/smothersbrot.htm)
Scope and Content
The collection consists of bound volumes of scripts for Smothers Brothers television variety show, The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour. Included are versions of final draft scripts. Guests represented among the scripts include Eddie Albert, The Beatles, Harry Belafonte, Jack Benny, George Burns, Glenn Campbell, Betty Davis, Jefferson Airplane, Jackie Moms Mabley, The Nitty Gritty Dirt Band, Pete Seeger, and Ravi Shankar, among others.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Collection PASC 36
Smothers Brothers television scripts and production material (Collection PASC 36). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Collection PASC-M 36
Smothers Brothers musical arrangements (Collection PASC-M 36) Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour Collections
Available at the UCLA Film and Television Archive.
Smothers Brothers--Archives; Smothers Brothers comedy hour
- Airdate: 2/5/1967 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  1ST, 2ND, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: NABORS, JIM; ST. JOHN, JILL; SULLIVAN, ED.
- Airdate: 2/12/1967 (Box 1)
  FINAL DRAFT, 2 COPIES. GUESTS: ALBERT, EDDIE; GABOR, EVA.
- Airdate: 2/19/1967 (Box 1)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: BENNY, JACK; BURNS, GEORGE; OFARIM, ESTHER.
- Airdate: 2/26/1967 (Box 1)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: DAVIS, BETTE; CRANE, BOB.
- Airdate: 3/5/1967 (Box 2)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: EDEN, BARBARA; PAUL REVERE & THE RAIDERS; REINER, CARL.
- Airdate: 3/12/1967 (Box 2)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: BURNETT, CAROL; BAJA MARIMBA BAND.
- Airdate: 3/19/1967 (Box 2)
  FINAL DRAFT, 2 COPIES. GUESTS: STEVENS, INGER; DURANTE, JIMMY; THE TURTLES; KERR, ANITA.
- Airdate: 3/26/1967 (Box 2)
  FIRST, SECOND, FINAL. GUESTS: JONES, JACK; SID & MARTY KROFFT'S PUPPETS; RANDALL, TONY.
- Airdate: 4/9/1967 (Box 3)
  FIRST, FINAL (2 COPIES). GUESTS: MAY, ELAINE; OFARIM, ESTHER; BLUE MAGOOS.
- Airdate: 4/16/1967 (Box 3)
  SECOND, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: MORSE, ROBERT; PAULSEN, PAT; TURNER, LANA; THE ELECTRIC PRUNES.
- Airdate: 4/23/1967 (Box 3)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: GARY, JOHN; O'BRIEN, MARGARET; SIMON & GARFUNKEL.
- Airdate: 4/30/1967 (Box 3)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: SINATRA, NANCY; SINATRA, FRANK, JR.; DE LUISE, DOM.
- Airdate: 5/7/1967 (Box 4)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: WILSON, NANCY; RAULSEN, PAT; WINTERS, JONATHAN; JEFFERSON AIRPLANE.
- Airdate: 5/14/1967 (Box 4)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: LEIGH, JANET; SIMON & GARFUNKEL.
- Airdate: 5/21/1967 (Box 4)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: LANDAU, MARTY; BAIN, BARBARA; PAULSEN, PAT.
- Airdate: 5/28/1967 (Box 5)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: BACKUS, JIM; O'BRIEN, MARGARET; THE ASSOCIATION.
- Airdate: 6/2/1967 (Box 5)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: CARR, VIKKI; ALLEN, STEVE; TEDDY NEELY FIVE.
- Airdate: 6/11/1967 (Box 5)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: JONES, SHIRLEY; HARRISON, NOEL; THE BUCKINGHAMS.
- Airdate: 6/18/1967 (Box 5)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: GARY, JOHN; GRIMES, TAMMY; THE BUCKINGHAMS.
- Airdate: 6/25/1967 (Box 6)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: DAVIS, BETTE; OFARIM, ESTER & ABI; PAULSEN, PAT; RANDALL, TONY; JONES, JACK.
- Airdate: 9/10/1967 (Box 6)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: LEIGH, JANET; SEEGER, PETE; GENTRY, BOBBIE; PAULSEN, PAT.
- Airdate: 9/17/1967 (Box 7)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: ROONEY, MICKEY; PAULSEN, PAT; DAVIS, BETTE; THE WHO.
- Airdate: 9/17/1967 (Box 7)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: BURNS, GEORGE; PAULSEN, PAT; HERMAN'S HERMITS.
- Airdate: 10/1/1967 (Box 8)
  FIRST, SECOND, FINAL. GUESTS: HARRISON, NOEL; CAKE, THE; PAULSEN, PAT; TURNER, LANA.
- Airdate: 10/8/1967 (Box 6)
  SECOND, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: PAULSEN, PAT; GARSON, GREER; THE ASSOCIATION.
- Airdate: 10/15/1967 (Box 8)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: SMITH, KATE; SCHELL, RONNIE; PAULSEN, PAT; SIMON & GARFUNKEL.
- Airdate: 10/22/1967 (Box 9)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: ALBERT, EDDIE; MABLEY, JACKIE; PAULSEN, PAT; THE BYRDS.
- Airdate: 10/29/1967 (Box 9)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: JONES, SHIRLEY; PAULSEN, PAT; BLACKSTONE, JR.; THE NITTY GRITTY DIRT BAND.
- Airdate: 11/5/1967 (Box 8)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: CRAWFORD, JOAN; PAULSEN, PAT; THE ASSOCIATION.
- Airdate: 11/12/1967 (Box 9)
  FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: MASON, JAMES; RODGERS, JIMMIE; FRYE, DAVID; PAULSEN, PAT; FELDON, BARBARA.
- Airdate: 11/19/1967 (Box 9)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: WILSON, NANCY; PAULSEN, PAT; SEGAL, GEORGE; PAUL REVERE & THE RAIDERS.
- Airdate: 11/26/1967 (Box 10)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: AMES, NANCY; IAN, JANIS; PAULSEN, PAT; DURANTE, JIMMY.
- Airdate: 12/10/1967 (Box 10)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: MOOREHEAD, AGNES; CROSBY, NORM; PAULSEN, PAT; THE HOLLIES.
- Airdate: 12/17/1967 (Box 10)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: BANKHEAD, TALLULAH; PAULSEN, PAT; THE TEMPTATIONS.
- Airdate: 12/24/1967 (Box 11)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: FABRAY, NANETTE; VALLE, MARCOS; PAULSEN, PAT; BENNY, JACK.
- Airdate: 12/31/1967 (Box 6)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: ALBERT, EDDIE; COLLINS, JUDY; THE IRISH ROVERS.
- Airdate: 1/7/1968 (Box 11)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: BERGEN, EDGAR; CARNE, JUDY; THE FIRST EDITION.
- Airdate: 1/14/1968 (Box 11)
  FIRST, FINAL. GUESTS: DUKE, PATTY; PAULSEN, PAT; RICKLES, DON; THE ASSOCIATION.
- Airdate: 1/21/1968 (Box 12)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: CAESAR, SID; CAMPBELL, GLENN; PAULSEN, PAT; BLACKSTONE RANGERS.
- Airdate: 1/28/1968 (Box 12)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: MORSE, ROBERT; PAULSEN, PAT; FABRAY, NANETTE; PAUL REVERE & THE RAIDERS.
- Airdate: 2/4/1968 (Box 12)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: GODFREY, ARTHUR; MABLEY, JACKIE "MOMS"; PAULSEN, PAT; FRENCH, LEIGH; THE BEE GEES.
- Airdate: 2/11/1968 (Box 13)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: KNOTTS, DON; SHANKAR, RAVI; PAULSEN, PAT; TORME, MEL.
- Airdate: 2/18/1968 (Box 13)
  FINAL DRAFTS, 3 COPIES. GUESTS: SINATRA, NANCY; SINATRA, FRANK, JR.; PAULSEN, PAT; JULLIARD STRING QUARTET.
- Airdate: 2/25/1968 (Box 13)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: SEEGER, PETE; PAULSEN, PAT; FRENCH, LEIGH.
- Airdate: 3/3/1968 (Box 14)
  FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: CAMPBELL, GLENN; MABLEY, JACKIE "MOMS"; HARTFORD, JOHN; PAULSEN, PAT.
- Airdate: 3/10/1968 (Box 14)
  FIRST, FINAL DRAFTS. GUESTS: CAMPBELL, GLENN; BROTHERS, JOYCE, DR..
- Airdate: 9/29/1968 (Box 14)
  FINAL DRAFT, 2 COPIES. GUESTS: ELLIOT, CASS; PAULSEN, PAT; BELAFONTE, HARRY.
- Airdate: 10/13/1968 (Box 14)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: FELDON, BARBARA; MEDLEY, BILL.
- Airdate: 10/27/1968 (Box 14)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: STEINBERG, DAVID; PAULSEN, PAT; EVERLY BROTHERS; NEW DAY SINGERS; LEONARD, JACK E..
- Airdate: 11/3/1968 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: CAMPBELL, GLENN; FRENCH, LEIGH; PAULSEN,PAT; CLINGER SISTERS.
- Airdate: 11/10/1968 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: WILLIAMS, MASON; PAULSEN, PAT; SMITH, KATE; JEFFERSON AIRPLANE.
- Airdate: 11/17/1968 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: DION; WARREN, JENNIFER; DONOVAN; THE COMMITTEE.
- Airdate: 11/24/1968 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: RANDALL, TONY; WARREN, JENNIFER; PAULSEN, PAT.
- Airdate: 12/8/1968 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: HAMPTON, PAUL; NEWHART, BOB; HAIR CAST; FIRST EDITION.
- Airdate: 12/22/1968 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: GOBEL, GEORGE; SPANKY & OUR GANG;;.
- Airdate: 1/5/1969 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: PAULSEN, PAT; FABRAY, NANETTE; STEPPENWOLF; THE FATHERS.
- Airdate: 1/12/1969 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: SMOTHERS BROS. WRITING STAFF; TOM & DICK SMOTHERS.
- Airdate: 1/19/1969 (Box 15)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: MASON, JACKIE; CHARLES, RAY.
- Airdate: 1/26/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: FRENCH, LEIGH; WILLIAMS, ANDY; THE CLINGERS.
- Airdate: 2/2/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: FRENCH, LEIGH; IVES, BURL; THE CHAMBERS BROTHERS; JACKIE & ROY.
- Airdate: 2/16/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: FRYE, DAVID; LIBERACE; HEDGE & DONNA.
- Airdate: 2/23/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: BORGE, VICTOR; SOUTH, JOE; THE BEATLES; THE HELLO PEOPLE; THE CLINGERS.
- Airdate: 3/2/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: COLLINS, JUDY; FRENCH, LEIGH; WINTERS, JONATHAN.
- Airdate: 3/9/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: BAEZ, JOAN; HARTFORD, JOHN; MASON, JACKIE; THE COMMITTEE; APRIL & NINO.
- Airdate: 3/23/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: SAHL, MORT; WARREN, JENNIFER; DONOVAN; PETER, PAUL, AND MARY.
- Airdate: 4/6/1969 (Box 16)
  FINAL DRAFT. GUESTS: PAULSEN, PAT; WILLIAMS, MASON; ROSE, BIFF; IKE & TINA TURNER.